<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Best choyce a funerall sermon / published at the desire of some of the friends of the dead.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18615</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5141.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S288</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22218358</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22218358</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25239</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18615)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1748:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Best choyce a funerall sermon / published at the desire of some of the friends of the dead.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 6-61 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for C.B. dwelling at the Swan in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸(-A1?) B-C⁸ D⁷.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians I, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25239:1"/>
            <p>THE BEST CHOYCE. A Funerall <hi>Sermon.</hi> Publiſhed at the deſire of <hi>ſome of the friends of</hi> the Dead.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 116.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Right deare in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>C. B.</hi> dwelling at the Swan in Pauls Church-yard. 1607.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:25239:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25239:2"/>
            <head>THE BEST choyce. A Funerall Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Philip. 1.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Deſiring to be looſed and to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text that I haue choſen, being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as it ſtandeth here related, is but a part of a ſentence. For in this verſe with the 22. going before, and the 24. following, the Apoſtle conſulteth of two things ſet before him, whether hee maye chooſe: not of any inconſtant light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, neither of any diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but becauſe he ſeeth in either thing good cauſe to deſire it.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:25239:3"/>
            <p>The two things whereof he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulteth whether to chooſe, are life and death: (in which conſultation moſt men would quickly reſolue. For many deſire life with any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, as <hi>Augustine</hi> truly affirmes in one of his Sermons, ſaying: <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam vitam, etiam malam pene omnes volunt habere:</hi> all men welnie deſire a long long life, though euill and troubleſome).</p>
            <p>The commoditie of life, for which the Apoſtle can bee content to chooſe it, is the profitable ſeruice that hee might doe to the Church. This he mentioneth as drawing his deſire after life in the 24. verſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Neuertheleſse, to abide in the fleſh is more needefull for you.</hi> Where note by the way, what it is ſhould make thee deſirous to liue in this world, onely to profit others, and to do the office of a good ſeruant among thy fellow ſeruants.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:25239:3"/>
            <p>The commoditie of death for which hee wiſheth, that is, the fellowſhippe of Chriſt in heauen ſo to be obtained. This hee men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth as drawing his deſire after it, in the wordes of my Text, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Deſiring to bee looſed and to bee with Christ, which is best of all.</hi> Where note I pray you, what is the hope &amp; deſire of the godly in their death, namely, to be gathered to their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</p>
            <p>If wee conſider theſe wordes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, ſingled from the reſt of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, they containe a perfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction concerning the death of true beleeuers: wherein are theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that death is a thing of the godly to be deſired, in theſe words, <hi>Deſiring to be looſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that the godlie are gathered by death, into the companie of Ieſus Chriſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25239:4"/>(which is the thing that maketh their death to be ſo much (to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired) in theſe wordes: <hi>and to bee with Chriſt.</hi> Thirdly, that the fellowſhip of Chriſt, which the godly obtaine after death, is the greateſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that can bee deſired or obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in theſe wordes: <hi>for that is beſt of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Text I haue choſen at this time for this reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We are come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; childe of God, who with all his hart deſired to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Who deſired his diſſolution with the ſame reaſon for which the Apoſtle deſired it; namely, that hee might be with Chriſt: and deſired this fellowſhippe of Chriſt, with the ſame iudgement, with which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle deſired it, becauſe hee knew that to be beſt of all.</p>
            <p>By the handling of this text, you ſhal ſee the wiſedom of of his choice
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25239:4"/>and his deſire, and ſo, I hope, bee drawen with deſire and iudgement to wait for the day of your diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you alſo may bee gathered to Chriſt, which is beſt of all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſiring to be looſed, eis to analuſai:</hi> for ſo the Apoſtle deſcribeth death to bee an vnbinding and looſing of man, that the ſoule ſet at liberty from the fetters of the fleſh, may return to his Creator freely. Which it cannot doe ſo long as it is ſhackled here in the body. And this deſcription of death is moſt conuenient both to confute all Sadduces, and alſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vs howe to iudge rightly of death.</p>
            <p>Euery childe of man is compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of theſe two parties: of an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane body, that is as the houſe and dwelling, and of a reaſonable ſoule, that is the tenant dwelling there. So are wee taught in the hiſtorie of the firſt mans creation. <hi>Gen. 2.7. The
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25239:5"/>Lord Gad made the man of the duſt of the ground,</hi> there is the body, the houſe of clay; <hi>and hee breathed in his face the breath of life.</hi> That is, ſaith <hi>Tremelius, Animam vitalem elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari corpori inſpirauit:</hi> by inſpiration hee placed a liuing ſoule in his ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie bodie, and the man was a liuing ſoule, ſo ſoone as theſe two partes beeing ioyned together the man liueth.</p>
            <p>And that which we cal death, is no thing elſe but the diſſoluing of this compoſition, and the ſeperating of theſe two parts, that the ſoule may be looſe and at liberty to returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, as <hi>Salomon</hi> deſcribeth death in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes, 12.7. Duſt returneth to earth as it was, and the ſpirit returnes to God that gaue it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Death is not the deſtruction, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the whole man, or of any part of him, as many ſuppoſe, that ſay in the Booke of Wiſedome, 2.2.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25239:5"/>
               <hi>Wee were borne at all auenture, and hereafter wee ſhall bee as if wee had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beene. For the breath is a ſmoke in our noſthrills, and the words are a ſparke raiſed out of the heart, which being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, the bodie is turned into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, and the ſpirit vaniſheth as the ſoft aire.</hi> Thus fooliſh men thinke that in death they periſh and come to nothing, and die as the beaſts doe.</p>
            <p>And of this opinion, in the Church of the Iewes, were the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd Saduces, who beleeued no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection to come of the body, and therefore thought that the body pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in death. And they belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that there was no ſpirit ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from fleſh, no ſuch inuiſible and ſpirituall creature, and therefore thought that the ſoule periſhed in death. Their abſurd opinion is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in <hi>Acts,</hi> 23.8. <hi>The Sadduces ſay, that there is no reſurrection, nor Spirit, nor Angel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:25239:6"/>
            <p>But we beleeue and teach contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to all Sadduces, both the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the ſoule remaining after death, and alſo the reſurrection of the fleſh at the laſt day. For the ſoule of <hi>Lazarus</hi> being dead, aſcended to a place of comfort. <hi>Luk. 16.22.</hi> And all that are in the graue (which is the receptacle of our dead bodies) ſhall at the laſt daye heare the voyce of Chriſt, ſending forth his Archangel with the ſound of a Trumpet, and they ſhall come forth to iudgement. <hi>Ioh. 5.28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that neither body nor ſoule in death periſheth and ceaſeth to bee: and death is no deſtruction of man, but the looſing of the Spirrit out of the priſon of the fleſh, and a diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of man into his parts, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle here ſpeaketh, deſiring to bee diſſolued. Wherein it behoueth no man to bee an agent, to looſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as they which lay violent hands
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25239:6"/>vpon themſelues: but we muſt all be patients, and wait vpon God, till he that tied the knot of life in thee, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the ſame. The Apoſtle, to bee with Chriſt, deſired not to loſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but to be looſed.</p>
            <q>Deſiring to be looſed.</q>
            <p>The Apoſtle in theſe words ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs his deſire: and in his deſire, ſheweth vs that death and deſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a thing to bee deſired of the godly. When the labourer hath wrought ſtoutly in the vineyard all the day, and at length the euening commeth wherein he may reſt, hee is glad of it, yea hee doth deſire and wait for the comming of the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that he may reſt. Our life here beneath, is but as a day, and a ſhort winter day; and here vpon the earth as in the Lords vineyard, we are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to labour: ſo the Parable of the labourers hired to worke in the vineyard, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. doth teach vs.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25239:7"/>When the euening of our daye, namely, death dooth come, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God reioyceth that he may reſt from his labour: yea, in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hee ſhoulde deſire the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of it, that hee might reſt from his labour: for death bringeth ſuch reſt. The holy Ghoſt from heauen affirmed to <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt, <hi>Reu. 14.13.</hi> that they which die in the Lord, doe reſt from their labours, and are therein bleſſed. And a wiſe Poet truly ſaide it, <hi>Eſt finis miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria in morte,</hi> in death our miſeries end.</p>
            <p>When the ſouldier hath put on armour, and lieth in Campe againſt the enemie, hee longeth for victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that hee may put off his armour, and reſt from that daungerous and painefull ſeruice. And when that wiſhed day is come, hee reioyceth for his reſt. For as the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> anſwered the king of <hi>Aram,</hi> though
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25239:7"/>he that girdeth on his armour boaſt himſelfe, yet he that putteth it off af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter victorie, hath whereof to boaſt. Now wee are all Souldiers, and our life vpon the earth is a warfare. So <hi>Ierome</hi> reades the firſt wordes of the ſeuenth chapter of <hi>Iob, Milita est vita hominis ſuper terram:</hi> A warfare ſaith hee, fighting againſt inuiſible aduerſaries. And wee are ſent into this world as the Lordes preſt men, vnder the Banner of Chriſt, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him our Captaine, to fight againſt ſinne, againſt the fleſh, the diuell, and the worlde, by dooing good workes, and reſiſting tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Sinne fighteth againſt vs, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten taketh vs captiues. <hi>Rom. 7.23. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I ſee an other Lawe in my m<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ebers rebelling againſt the Law of my minde, and leading mee captiue vnto the law of ſin which is in my members.</hi> The fleſh fighteth againſt vs, ſtriuing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25239:8"/>againſt the ſpirit, as the ſpirit ſtriueth againſt the fleſh. And <hi>Peter</hi> biddeth vs, <hi>Abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, becauſe they fight againſt the ſoule. 1. Pet. 2.11.</hi> The Diuell commeth fiercely vpon vs as a roaring Lyon, and fighteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. <hi>Eph. 6.16.</hi> beeing armed with fierie darts. And the worlde dooth not loue thoſe whom God hath choſon out of the world. <hi>Iohn, 15.19.</hi> and the battel which we haue to maintaine againſt thoſe enemies is moſt perillous, becauſe, <hi>Eph. 6.22.</hi> wee wraſtle not againſt fleſh and blood, but againſt principalities and powers, againſt the worldly gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, the princes of the darkneſſe of this world.</p>
            <p>This battell endeth not till the day of our diſſolution commeth: then are wee freed from tentations, and deliuered from ſinne. For <hi>Romans, 6.7.</hi> the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>Hee that is dead is freed from ſinne.</hi> Then doe wee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25239:8"/>reſt and reioyce, triumphing ouer all our enemies, ſauing that death for a time holdeth our bodies in the duſt of the earth. And therefore the day of our diſſolution, as the end of our both painefull and dangerous warre is to be deſired.</p>
            <p>Hee that can diſcerne betweene labour with wearineſſe, &amp; reſt with reward, betweene warre with perill, and victorie with ioyfull peace, hee will ſay, that the daye of death to a good man is to bee deſired more then life; becauſe life is labour with wearineſſe, and woe with perill: but the houre of death bringeth reſt with reward, and victorie with ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full peace. <hi>Ciprian</hi> in a Treatiſe of his, <hi>De mortalitate,</hi> in the third ſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſaith of life; <hi>Quid aliud in mundo quam pugna aduerſus diabolum quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die geritur? quam aduerſus iacula eius &amp; tela conflictationibus aſsidius dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur?</hi> While wee are in the world,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25239:9"/>what do we but fight againſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell? and warre with continual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts againſt his arrowes and darts? but of death hee ſaith: <hi>Illa est pax no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, illa fida tranquillitas, illa ſtabilis, &amp; firma, &amp; perpetua ſecuritas:</hi> Death is our peace, our ſure tranquilitie, our ſtable, firme and perpetual ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Balaam</hi> that falſe Prophet, that loued the wages of iniquitie, beeing hired by the King of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab</hi> to curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had conſidered that curſing could not bee the ende of Gods people, but that they were heires of bleſſing, hee pronounced theſe wordes, <hi>Numbers, 23.10. Let mee die the death of the righteous: let my last end be like his.</hi> The man did ſee, his eyes beeing opened of God, that the end of the righteous, for the peace and happineſſe thereof was to be deſired.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:25239:9"/>
            <p>The day of diſſolution to a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man, is like that day in which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was brought out of priſon, and ſtoode before <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> Hee had long beene in bonds. In pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hee was baſely clothed as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a priſoner. In the end his fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are laid aſide, hee is taken out of priſon, he putteth off his baſe attire, he is waſhed and ſhauen, hee put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on new apparrell, is brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of the King, and made a ruler throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>The iuſt mans life is like the time of his captiuitie; and his death is like to his deliuerie. While wee liue, the ſoule is incloſed in the bodie as in a priſon, and is clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the fleſh, as with fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie garmentes, and is clog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with ſinne, as with fetters of yron and braſſe; and is cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with iniuries and tentations,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25239:10"/>more greeuous and noyſome then the hunger, colde, and noyſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the priſon.</p>
            <p>But when the houre of diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on commeth, the priſon is broken, and wee are deliuered. Wee put off the ragges of the fleſh, and are clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with white: we are looſed from the fetters of ſinne, we are waſhed in the blood of Chriſt, wee are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the preſence of God, and are made togither with Ieſus Chriſt heires of a heauenly kingdom. And therefore as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> deſired to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, and had cauſe to riot when that daye came, euen ſo may the righteous deſire their diſſolution, &amp; they haue cauſe to reioyce when the day thereof draweth nigh.</p>
            <p>The death indeed of the wicked is very fearefull, and by all meanes to be auoided, if it could bee auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: For their death is like the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ſlothfull ſeruant, when
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25239:10"/>his Maiſter will examine his daies worke. It is like the comming home of the Lorde to the vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, that had wrapped his Tallent in a napkin, and buried it in the ground: hee was called to account, and becauſe he had beene idle, <hi>Mat. 25.26.</hi> his Talent was taken from him, and giuen to an other, and after ſharpe rebukes, hee was caſt into vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter darkneſſe, where is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. It is like the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſiſes, and day of goale deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto the malefactor, who being brought from the priſon to the Bar, and there condemned, is led from thence to the place of execution. It is like the birth day of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> vnto his officer the Baker, who was taken out of priſon, led to the gallowes, hanged, and made a praie to the foules of heauen.</p>
            <p>The death therefore of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked is euill, and to be ſhunned (if it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25239:11"/>could bee ſhunned) for in it endeth all their reſt, and beginneth all their labour. In it, endeth all their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and beginneth all their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. In it endeth all their pleaſure, &amp; beginneth their torment, which neuer ſhall end: and they fall as the tree that is cut downe for the fire. Reade the report of the vnmercifull glutton, in <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.19. what pleaſures his life abounded withall; which all turned to torments when hee died.</p>
            <p>But the righteous are cut downe like to ripe corne, that with care is brought into the barne: and they are deliuered from the euills that are to come. <hi>Eſay,</hi> 57.1. they reſt from all their labours paſt. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.13. They come to their perfect ioy, in hope whereof they reioyced bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.11. It is ſaide to the good ſeruant, <hi>Enter into thy Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ioy.</hi> And when they put off the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25239:11"/>earthly houſe of this tabernacle, 2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 5.1. they haue a building gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of God, not made with handes, but eternall in heauen. They leaue earthly poſſeſſions, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming naked into the worlde, they found here, and going naked out of the world, they leaue here: and for them they receiue an inheritance immortal, vndefiled, that fadeth not away, but is reſerued for them in the heauens: and then doe they truly begin to liue, when they depart out of this darke vale of fraile morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
            <p>Truly that ſeruant of God (the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of whoſe earthly tabernacle lie here before vs to be interred) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the death of the righteous was to bee deſired, did with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and longing, expect and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine the houre of his diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And when hee had, not yet in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25239:12"/>deede, but onely in his purpoſe and reſolution, put off his fleſh, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in himſelfe the ſentence of death, hee could by no meanes bee drawen in his affections to put it on againe, though the fraile fleſh and his fading life, as enticing harlots, did earneſtly ſtriue to drawe his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto them.</p>
            <p>But as a wiſe and ſtout trauailer, when after long &amp; wearie iournies, he ſees at laſt, not farre off, the place of his habitation, dooth then with double deſire contend to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; and wil not then ſuffer himſelfe to bee ſtaied, but ſaith in his heart, Oh long deſired ſeate of my wiſhed reſt, often haue I thoght vpon thee, now ſhall I obtaine thee: my feete forget their wearineſſe, and my hart forgets all faintnes, for loue of thee: and my deſire ſhall not end, till I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the end of my deſire.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo this man, made wiſe by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25239:12"/>the word of God, which maketh wiſe vnto ſaluation, &amp; being ſtrong and of good courage in the Lorde, when after wearie trauaile and long iournies, in this wilderneſſe of the world, &amp; vale of tentations, he was admoniſhed by ſickneſſe and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, that he was not farre from the end of his way, and that his reſting place vpon the hill of Gods holines was not much diſtant: hee lifted vp the eyes of his minde toward hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and contemplating the beautie of the heauenly new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and of the glorious kingdome prepared for the ſonnes of God; with doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led deſire he contended thither, and caſting of all thoſe things that might ſtay him (the loue of this world and of fraile life) hee wholly breathed heauen, with this reſolution; Long haue I deſired thee, nowe haue I found thee. When thou wert fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of I deſired thee, and now that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25239:13"/>my ioy be fulfilled in comming vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not theſe things as onely intending to praiſe him, though it be his iuſt and great praiſe that theſe things be truly ſpoken of him, and ſuch a praiſe as men doe not vſually deſerue, namely, to renounce this world, &amp; to contend, with ful courſe of ſtrong affections toward heauen. For his praiſe only, I ſpeak not theſe things of him (though to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous there belongeth a bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, <hi>Prou.</hi> 10.7.) himſelfe deſired not praiſe among men, but the praiſe that is of God.</p>
            <p>But I remember alſo for your ſakes, and in him I ſhadow forth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you (as in an example agreeing aptly with the doctrine of my text) what ought to be the deſire and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of euery of you: namely, to meete the Lords purpoſe with your deſire, and to goe hence with ioy,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25239:13"/>when the houre of your diſſolution commeth, and not to looke backe in your loue and wiſhes, to this world, as <hi>Lots</hi> wife looked backe to <hi>Sodome,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her departure out from thence was her ſafetie, and her ſtay could not haue beene any longer without her hurt.</p>
            <p>Thus much ſhall ſerue to haue ſpoken of the firſt wordes, wherein the Apoſtle ſignifieth his deſire of death. Now let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie that he looketh to reape by his diſſolution, which maketh him ſo much to deſire it.</p>
            <q>And to be with Christ.</q>
            <p>The commoditie of life was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, hee might doe good to others. His wordes for that, are in verſe 24. <hi>Neuertheleſſe to abide in the fleſh is more needefull for you.</hi> The commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of death is priuate, he ſhall win good to himſelfe. That he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in the words of this verſe, <hi>Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25239:14"/>to bee diſſolued, and to bee with Chriſt.</hi> In which words, giuing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his deſire, hee teacheth vs a fruit of our death, and what it is that ſhould make vs deſire death, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that thereby we might be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Many men for many cauſes deſire the day of their diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But as the Lord Ieſus ſaid, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.42. of <hi>Maries</hi> choyce, <hi>One thing is needefull:</hi> ſo may we ſay of the reaſons, driuing men to deſire death, one is laudable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abimelech,</hi> the baſe ſonne of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon,</hi> beſieged a Tower in <hi>Tebez,</hi> and comming neare vnto the wall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, a woman threw down vpon him a peece of a milſtone, wherewith ſhe brake his head. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 9.53. Then he called his ſeruant that bare his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and bad him draw his ſword and kill him: yeelding this reaſon for his deſire of death; <hi>That men might not ſay, a woman killed him.</hi> The
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25239:14"/>valiant man, for the auoiding of that diſhonour, deſiring the ſpeede of his owne diſſolution, by his armour bearers hands.</p>
            <p>In the daies of <hi>Dauid, Abſolom</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt his father. And <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi> a man very politike, and a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till counſeller, tooke part with him. His counſell <hi>Abſolom</hi> refuſed, &amp; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed rather the counſell of <hi>Huſpai.</hi> Herevpon <hi>Achitophel,</hi> partly angrie, and diſdaining that his counſell was not followed, &amp; partly fearing that <hi>Abſoloms</hi> faction could not preuaile, letting ſlip the opportunitie that he had counſelled him to take, ſadled his Aſſe, forſooke <hi>Abſolom,</hi> went to his owne houſe, ſet all things in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and then hanged himſelfe. The proud Polititia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not able to beare the diſgrace, and fearing afterclaps, (for he ſuſpected <hi>Abſoloms</hi> fall) haſtened with his own hands his diſſolution. So <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitour, not able to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25239:15"/>beare the diſgrace of his owne trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in betraying the innocent blood of his Maiſter, made a quicke diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of himſelfe. <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.5.</p>
            <p>And not onely the wicked, but the godly alſo, haue ſometime ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened their death, and deſired the day of their diſſolution, vpon weake reaſons, which as I dare not diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, ſo I cannot greatly commend. When <hi>Sampſon,</hi> by the ſubtiltie of a Harlot, came into the handes of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> they put out his eyes, and cauſed him to grinde in a mill. And when on a certaine day, the Princes of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> were come togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſacrifice vnto <hi>Dagon</hi> their god, to whom they gaue the praiſe, to haue deliuered their enemie into their hands, then <hi>Sampſon</hi> was called for, hee muſt bee brought forth to make them merrie. And within a large houſe, whoſe waight was born vppe with two mighty pillars in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25239:15"/>middeſt, <hi>Sampſon</hi> was placed neare thoſe ſame pillars: who praying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God to ſtrengthen him, with all his power preſted the pillars, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrew the houſe, <hi>Iud.</hi> 16.30. and ſlew a great multitude. For there were without, vpon the roofe of the houſe, three thouſands, beſides them that were within: and among the multitude, he himſelfe periſhed. The good man conſidered that it was his calling to deſtroye the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the people of God; and hee loued not his life, that hee might with loſſe thereof, finiſh the worke of his calling.</p>
            <p>And good <hi>Elias,</hi> that zealous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of God, in the daies of <hi>Ahab,</hi> fleeing from <hi>Iezebel,</hi> into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe beyond <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> and ſitting vnder a Iuniper-tree, deſired to die, ſaying; 1. <hi>Kings,</hi> 19.4. <hi>It is enough O Lord, take away my life, I am no better then my fathers.</hi> Hee was ſomewhat
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25239:16"/>impatient, and would haue had his diſſolution haſtened, becauſe hee could reſt no where in ſafetie from the wrath of <hi>Iezebel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For many &amp; diuers cauſes, which for the time haue taken away the ſweetneſſe of life, and the bitterneſſe of death; many haue deſired the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening of their diſſolution. But ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſhort, vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant, &amp; not alwaies iuſtifiable, is the deſire grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe cauſes. Burdens preſſe vs not continually, that wee ſhould be euer weary of bearing. Perils indure not euer, that we ſhould euer feare. Reproach doth not alwaies attend vpon vs, that we ſhould out of a big heart miſlike our liues for ſhame. Paine and diſcontentment doe not abide with vs ſtill, that we ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wiſh to die: the deſire to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, grounded vpon theſe cauſes, cannot be laſting.</p>
            <p>There is onely one true reaſon,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25239:16"/>that taketh awaye all bitterneſſe of death, and ouercommeth all ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this preſent life, and bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in vs a true, conſtant and ſound deſire of diſſolution. And that is this, that the Apoſtle here remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth, as the commoditie or aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of death, drawing his deſire, namely, that by this meanes hee ſhould be gathered vnto Chriſt, and obtaine fellowſhippe with him by fight, and not by faith: the gaine, and glorie, and ſweetneſſe of which fellowſhip, wee ſhall conſider when we come to handle thoſe laſt words, <hi>(Which is beſt of all).</hi> Here it is more proper to conſider and ſhewe, that the fellowſhippe of Chriſt is gained by diſſolution, and that the godlie dying, doe goe vnto him.</p>
            <p>Of the two malefactors which was crucified with the Lorde Ieſus, the one vpon the Croſſe beſought him, ſaying: <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.42. <hi>Lord remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:25239:17"/>me when thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt into thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi> to whom hee made anſwer in the 43. verſe: <hi>This day thou ſhalt bee with me in Paradiſe.</hi> Of which fauour afforded to the theefe, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth excellently, writing vpon the 38. Pſalme, and framing a little ſhort ſpeech to the diuell, by whom <hi>Iudas</hi> had beene lately before ſet on to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray his Maſter. The theefe vpon the Croſſe, ſaith <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding ſawe the kingdome of Chriſt, which <hi>Iudas</hi> could not ſee in the feaſt &amp; Supper of Chriſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did this heauenly voyce ſecond the theeues praier, <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> Thou didſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ô fierce Dragon, that thou hadſt drawn away an Apoſtle from Chriſt, <hi>Plus amiſiſti quam ſuſtuliſti qui latronem vides in Paradiſum eſse tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatum:</hi> Thou haſt loſt more then thou haſt got, and ſo thinke when thou ſeeſt the theefe tranſlated into
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25239:17"/>Paradiſe. For who ſhal be excluded, when a theefe is admitted? Thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, ô diuell, entred thither from whence thou wert caſt out. But lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing further commenting vppon thoſe wordes, in them wee may ſee that the ſame day and houre when the ſoule of a true beleeuer depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from the body, it taketh a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie iourny, and is carried by Angells into Paradiſe, to enioy the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In the fourteenth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> verſe, 2. Ieſus ſaith: <hi>In my fathers houſe are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manſions. If it were not ſo, I would haue told you. I goe to prepare a place for you: and though I goe to prepare a place for you, I will come againe and receiue you vnto my ſelfe, that where I am, there may you bee alſo.</hi> His Fathers houſe that hee ſpeaketh of, is the ample kingdom of heauen: the many man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions there, are the bleſſed reſting places of the Saints: Ieſus went to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25239:18"/>prepare thoſe places in his aſcenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Hee commeth againe to euery one of vs in the houre of diſſolution, and by the miniſtery of Angels, receiues our ſoules to himſelfe, that in the ſame Kingdome they may reſt with him, till they receiue their bodies in the reſurrtction, when both in body and ſoule, they ſhall continue with him for euer. This promiſe of Chriſt to come againe and receiue them to himſelfe, did make them, ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> in his 77. Tractate vpon <hi>Iohn, Certes &amp; fidentes, post pericula tentatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ſe apud Deum cum Christo eſſe manſures:</hi> Sure and confident, that after the perill of tentations, that is, after death &amp; diſſolution, they ſhall continue with Chriſt in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God.</p>
            <p>Vnto that former place, ioyne an other teſtimonie out of <hi>Iohn,</hi> in his ſeuenteenth chapter, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the twenty verſe to the 25. Ieſus praieth for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:25239:18"/>thoſe that beleeue in him, that they might bee one with him by a moſt ſtrait coniunction. And in the verſe 24. that they ſhould come vnto him, ſaying: <hi>Father, I will that thoſe which thou hast giuen mee, be where I am, that they may ſee my glorie which thou hast giuen me, for thou didſt loue mee before the foundation of the world, I will,</hi> ſaith Ieſus, <hi>that they be where I am.</hi> Then, as hee left the world to aſcend vnto his Father, ſo they muſt leaue the world, which they doe in death, to aſcend vp vnto Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>A notable place is that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſecond to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, 5. chapter 6. verſe. <hi>Wee are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies bold, thogh we know that while we are at home in the body, we are abſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord: for wee walke by faith, and not by ſight: Neuertheleſſe we are bold, and loue rather to remoue out of the body, and to dwell with the Lord.</hi> So long as wee dwell in theſe houſes of clay, where
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:25239:19"/>faith is the ſtay and comfort of our ſoules. We are ſtrangers from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preſence &amp; companie of Chriſt, from heauen, &amp; from our Countrey and reſting place. We are not in <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria,</hi> but in <hi>via,</hi> not in our Countrey, but in the way vnto it. But when we put off the earthly houſe of this ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, <hi>Quam ſeperamur à corpore,</hi> ſaith <hi>Anſelme, preſentamur Domino, vt eum in ſpecie diuinitatis ſuae videamus, &amp; apud eum maneamus.</hi> That is, when we are ſeperated from the body, we are preſented to the Lord, that wee may ſee him in the ſhow and beauty of his diuinitie, and may remaine with him.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let vs conſider what wee read, <hi>Reuelations,</hi> 14.1. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſeeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thouſands ſtanding on Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> with the Lambe Ieſus Chriſt, They are in his company, and they follow the Lambe whither ſoeuer he goeth. Theſe places doe plainely
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25239:19"/>teach vs, that this followeth the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and death of the Saints, as a thing for which it is to bee deſired, that they do goe vnto the Lord, and inioy the company of Ieſus Chriſt their redeemer: their ſoules doe ſo when they die, and their bodies alſo in the reſurrection, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth in his firſt Epiſtle to the Theſſalonians, 4. chapter, 16. verſe, <hi>The Lord himſelf ſhal deſcend from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with a ſhout, and with the voyce of the Archangel, and with the trumpet of God: and the dead in Chriſt ſhal riſe firſt. Then ſhal we which liue and remaine, be caught vp with them alſo in the cloudes, to meete the Lorde in the aire: and ſo ſhal wee euer be with the Lord.</hi> But the body reſting in the graue, &amp; waiting for that glorious reſurrection, the ſoule in the meane time leauing the fleſh, and leauing the world, goeth to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>O bleſſed and moſt comfortable
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:25239:20"/>death of the Saints, which gathereth the members to the head in whom they liue: and ſetteth the branches cloſe to the tree in the liuely ſappe whereof they flouriſh: which brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth home the Bride into the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Bridegroome, in whom onely ſhee reioyceth: and gathereth the redeemed people together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their redeemer: who onely hath made them free, and leadeth vs out of this vale of miſerie, vnto our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that wee may ſee his glorie, and bee partakers with him of his kingdome.</p>
            <p>The worſt then that can be ſaid of death, for his doings vnto the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is this, that he is a cruell &amp; chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh guide, that leadeth vs vnto a moſt ſweet and curteous Lord: that he is a rough &amp; boiſterous miniſter, that performeth and dooth for vs a moſt acceptable ſeruice: that his countenance is much deformed, &amp;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25239:20"/>hee fraieth thoſe to whom hee appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: that his hands are burning hot, &amp; hee ſcorcheth thoſe whom he appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth. Yet among the faithfull, thoſe whom he laieth hold vpon, hee bringeth to Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This is not out of the naturall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of death, that the faithfull reape ſuch aduantage by it; for death was born of ſinne, which diuideth vs from God: and it was ordained as a heauie puniſhment of ſin, and it is ſtill a ſigne and remembrance of Gods anger for ſin. But this commeth to paſſe by the benefit and fauour of him, who by his death hath deſtroyed death, and him that had the power of death, that is, the diuell. It commeth to paſſe by the benefite of Ieſus Chriſt, who hath made vs more then conquerours ouer death &amp; euery aduerſary, taking away the ſting of death, &amp; making a plague to be a bleſſing, an enemie to be a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, becauſe now without death, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25239:21"/>is, otherwiſe then by the paſſage of death, fleſh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God. This commeth to paſſe by the merit of him, and by faith in him, who is vnto vs both in life and death aduantage, and whoſe wee are both liuing &amp; dying, that whether we ſleep or wake, we might liue togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaking of benefite, attained by death in this world, I meane this firſt death, in his 13. Booke of the Citie of God, and 4. chapter, ſaith: <hi>Non quia mors bonum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod facta eſt quae ante malum fuit: ſed tantam Deus fidei preſtitit gratiam vt mors, quam vitae conſtat eſse contrariam, inſtrumentum fieret per quod tranſiretur in vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> It is not becauſe death is now become a good thing and a bleſſing, which before was an euill thing and curſe: but ſo much grace hath God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorded to our faith in Chriſt, that death which was knowne to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to life &amp; happineſſe, ſhould now
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25239:21"/>become an inſtrument of our paſſage to life and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>And therefore not vnto death and diſſolution that dooth bring vs vnto Chriſt, but vnto Ieſus Chriſt, that by death and diſſolution doth bring and gather vs vnto himſelfe, doe wee giue thankes for this aduantage of our death, that when we are looſed, we go vnto the Lord, for dread full death, in <hi>tantam vtilitatem non vi ſua ſed diuina opitulatione conuerſa eſt:</hi> is become a matter of great profite to vs, not by it owne force &amp; vertue, but by the helpe of God. Yet from hence the faith full may learne &amp; gather vnto themſelues plentifull comfort againſt the terrours of death, and ſtrong incouragement, if not to deſire &amp; long for, yet to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine with reioycing the day of their diſſolution, becauſe from thenceforth they ſhall be with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This did that ſeruant of the Lord ſee, whoſe body wee followed to the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25239:22"/>graue. And therefore quietly, yea ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, hee accepted, yea deſired his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſometime ſaying; Come Lord Ieſus: and ſometime ſaying, I come Lord Ieſus: only deſiring, &amp; conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſiring to be with the Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <p>And this is it that ſhall make death (bitter in it ſelfe) to be both ſweet and pleaſant vnto vs, when it commeth. And therefore I beſeech you learne now in time, lay this doctrine vp in your harts, &amp; often think vpon it, that the faithfull departing hence, doe goe vnto the Lord, that when the houre commeth, whsch canot be auoided, we may embrace the pleaſure of God, as the meanes of our owne good, and may not murmure in vaine.</p>
            <p>But it may be, ſome will ſay, is it a matter of ſo great price to be gathered vnto Chriſt, that a man ſhould deſpiſe al the pleaſures of this life, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne all the bitternes &amp; terrors of the houre of death: &amp; with the Apoſtle here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25239:22"/>
               <hi>to be looſed, and to be with Chriſt!</hi> I ſurely, and that is it that followeth in the next place to bee conſidered, and in the laſt wordes of my text.</p>
            <q>Which is beſt of all.</q>
            <p>Vnto the Lord Ieſus at the laſt day, all both good and bad, ſhall be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the 25. of <hi>Matth:</hi> at the 31. verſe, It is ſaide, <hi>When the Sonne of man ſhall come in his glorie, and all his holy Angells with him, then ſhall he ſit vpon the throne of his glorie, and before him ſhall be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all Nations of the earth.</hi> And in the 2. to the Corinthians, 5. chapter, &amp; 10, verſe, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Wee muſt all appeare before the tribunall ſeate of Chriſt, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one may receiue the thinges that are done in his body, whether it be good or euil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All therefore at that day ſhall bee brought before the Lord Ieſus: But the wicked ſhal not come to be and to abide with Ieſus Chriſt from that day. Neither ſhal they in the houre of their diſſolution bee gathered vnto him, to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25239:23"/>be &amp; abide with him before that day. They ſhall come vnto him as vnto a Iudge, armed with authoritie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne. They ſhall come vnto him as vnto a reuenger, appearing from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with flaming fire to deſtroy. And their iudgement when they appeare, ſhal be to depart for euer from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. As wee reade the ſentence ſet downe in the 25. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> at the 14. verſe, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire, prepared for the diuell and his angells.</hi> And of the iudgment of them, in that great day, that either know not God, hauing had no calling, or obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, hauing obeied no calling, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, in the ſecond to the Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, 1. chapter, and 9. verſe, <hi>That they ſhall be puniſhed with euerlaſting perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glorie of his power.</hi> Their comming therefore is not to bee and abide with Chriſt. And for the time of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25239:23"/>and abiding before Chriſt, it ſhall be moſt fearefull vnto them: of whom it is written, <hi>Reuelations</hi> 6. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 16. verſe, <hi>That they ſhall ſay vnto the mountaines and hills, fall vpon vs, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from the preſence of him that ſitteth vpon the throne, and from the Lambe, for the great day of his wrath is come, and who can ſtand?</hi> (that is, who ſhall be able to abide his iudgement)?</p>
            <p>But the faithfull at that great day come vnto him, to be, and abide with him: to whom Ieſus ſhal ſay in the 25. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> 34. <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father.</hi> And of whom <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſay, in the 1. to the Theſſalonians, 4. chap: 17. verſe, <hi>So ſhal we be euer with the Lord.</hi> And that their being and continuing with him is their happines, as here <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Euen beſt of all.</hi> To this purpoſe it is an apt ſpeech that is in the 6. chapter of <hi>Auguſtines Manuale, Faelix anima quae terreno reſoluta tarcere libera coelum petit, quae te dulciſimum Dominum facie
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25239:24"/>ad faciem ceruit, quae nullo metu mortis affiicitur, ſed de incorruptione perpetua gloria letatur.</hi> Happy is that ſoule, which freed from her earthly priſon, dooth now in libertie enter into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and there beholdeth thee moſt ſweete Lord Ieſus, face to face, and is affected with no more feare of death, but reioyceth in the incorruptible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of eternall glory.</p>
            <p>Marke the words of the Lord Ieſus ſpoken to the Apoſtles, touching this very matter of his fellowſhip in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and you ſhall finde them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne all conſolation. In the 22. of <hi>Luke,</hi> at the 29. verſe, <hi>I appoint vnto you a kingdome, as my Father hath appointed to me, that you may eate and drinke at my table in my kingdome, and ſit on thrones, iudging the twelue Tribes of Iſrael.</hi> In the fellowſhippe of Chriſt they ſhall bee made partakers with him of all glorie and gladneſſe, they ſhall be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with him of all glorie: for they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25239:24"/>raigne with him as Kings, and be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partners of his Kingdome, and ioyne with him in iudgement, when he ſhall condemne the wicked. And they ſhall bee made partakers with him of all gladneſſe, for they ſhall ſit with him at table, after the bleſſed manner of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly entertainement, and they ſhall eate and drinke with him, after the manner of heauenly diet, and it ſhall be done to them that was ſaide to the faithfull ſeruant, they ſhall enter into their Maiſters ioy.</p>
            <p>The bleſſedneſſe of this fellowſhip is deſcribed and ſhadowed forth vnto vs in the Parable, by the happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the fiue wiſe Virgins, of whom it is ſaid in the 25. verſe of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> 10. verſe, <hi>That they entred with the Bridegroome into his wedding Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> What meane theſe thinges, the wedding day is a day of ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? The place where the wedding is kept, is a place abounding with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:25239:25"/>and feaſting. Thoſe that are gueſts, admitted to the fellowſhip of that time and place, and admitted to the fellowſhippe of ioy and gladneſſe. The wine was merely ſpent at the wedding in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> when the company was ſober, and Ieſus, his mother, and Diſciples were bidden and preſent. And the faithfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Ieſus, (for the ſtate of all the faithful in thoſe fiue wiſe Virgins is ſhadowed) enter with him into the wedding chamber: that is, they come to the place of mirth, of ioy, and of gladneſſe. Where, as <hi>Anſelme</hi> ſaith, <hi>Munda anima ſempiterno diuino conſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio copulatur:</hi> The pure ſoule is cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled as in marriage, with euerlaſting fellowſhip with God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Father,</hi> ſaith Ieſus in the 17. of <hi>Iohn,</hi> 24. verſe, <hi>I will that thoſe which thou hast giuen me, be with me where I am, that they may ſee my glory which thou haſt giuen mee.</hi> That is, that at leiſure and at their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:25239:25"/>pleaſure, they may ſatisfie their ſoules with viewing whatſoeuer delight the Kingdome of heauen, and the glorie of the Sonne of God may affoord. Which how great delight it is vnto the ſoule, they cannot conceiue that are not yet admitted to ſee.</p>
            <p>The Queene of the South, came a far iourney, to ſee the wiſedome, the riches, the glorie of <hi>Salomon,</hi> whereof ſhe had heard report. And in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> 9. chapter, ſhe came and ſaw, and wondred. And in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth verſe, pronounced the ſeruants of <hi>Salomon</hi> and his men happy; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſtoode before him &amp; heard his wiſedome.</p>
            <p>And when wee ſhall come vnto Chriſt to continue with him, and to ſtand before him; is there not a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>Salomon</hi> there? In wiſedome, and riches, and glory, farre paſſing <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon?</hi> How much more then ſhall we be happie and bleſſed, to heare his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:25239:26"/>wiſedome, in whom all the treaſure of wiſedome and knowledge are lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp? <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee had the wordes of eternall life in his mouth, whiles he was poore and deſpiſed on earth.</hi> His wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome then muſt needes be the words of eternall comfort and glorie, which his followers ſhall heare from his mouth in heauen.</p>
            <p>And how much more ſhall we be happie in beholding his riches and glorie, when wee ſhall obtaine with him all vſe of his riches, and ſhall bee transformed into the like glorie? For the iuſt ſhall ſhine as the Sunne in the Kingdome of their Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.43.</p>
            <p>The beautie of Lillies and other flowers exceedeth, by the ſaying of our Sauiour Chriſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.29. the beautie and glorie of <hi>Salomon.</hi> But the glorie of the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt farre exceedeth the glorie of the heauens, his exceeding glorie giuing light and beautie to the heauens. As it is ſaid,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:25239:26"/>
               <hi>Reuelations,</hi> 21. chapter, and 23. verſe, <hi>The Citie of the heauenly Ieruſalem hath no neede of the Sun, neither of the Moone to ſhine in it, for the glorie of God did light it, and the Lambe is the light of it.</hi> Then neceſſarily it muſt giue much more true content and delight, and bee a greater happineſſe, to bee and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with Chriſt to ſee his glory, then to be &amp; abide in <hi>Salomons</hi> Court, and to ſee his glory.</p>
            <p>Yea ſo happy a thing it is to be with Chriſt, &amp; behold his glory, that when hee was transfigured vpon the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and had onely two of the Saints in company with him, <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Elias,</hi> and they conferring with him of no pleaſant diſcourſe, but of his death that hee ſhould ſhortly ſuffer at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> yet the view of that ſhort glorie, was ſo excellent in <hi>Peters</hi> iudgement, that though hee and his two fellowes were open to the checke of all wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the mountaines top, and were
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:25239:27"/>not themſelues inlightened and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with that glorie, yet was hee ſo wholly ſurpriſed and rauiſhed with the ſight of it, that hee would gladly there haue made his continual abode, to haue had libertie ſtill to behold the ſame: ſaying in the 17. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> 4. verſe, <hi>Maſter, it is good for vs to be here: if thou wilt, let vs make here three Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, one for thee, and one for Moſes, and one for Elias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider ſtill the circumſtances of that glorie of Chriſt which they then ſawe, and compare it with the reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led circumſtances of the preſent glory of Chriſt, which the ſoules of the faithfull now after diſſolution doe ſee in heauen: and it will appeare, that though it were a good thing, and a ſigne of great fauour, to bee admitted to ſee that glorie of Chriſt vppon the mountaine, yet it is as my text dooth call it, <hi>Multo magis melius,</hi> much better, beſt of all: and the full fruit of infinite
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:25239:27"/>fauour to be with Chriſt after diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to be admitted in heauen to behold his preſent glorie.</p>
            <p>The Lord Ieſus for his owne part did then ſhine in glorie, his face as the Sunne, his garments as the light. So that <hi>Peter</hi> doth call it, in his ſecond E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, 1. chapter, 16. verſe, <hi>Maiestie, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory:</hi> yet putting a difference betweene that and another, which he calleth excellent glory. From whence that voyce came, ſaying: <hi>This is my wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Ieſus was then vpon an earthly mountaine, vpon <hi>Mount Tabor,</hi> he was not then vpon <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> which <hi>Iohn</hi> in the <hi>Reuelations</hi> ſaw. And he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied onely with two of his Saints, wanting the honorable traine of an hundred fortie and foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, hauing his Fathers name vpon their fore-heads, and with heauenly muſicke attending him vppon that mountaine. And the glory of Ieſus in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:25239:28"/>that open and ſolitary place was ſhort. <hi>Peter</hi> heard <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Elias</hi> talking with him of his death that ſhould ſhortly follow at <hi>Ieruſalem. Peter</hi> alſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held that glory, was as ſlenderly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with <hi>Iames</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn,</hi> and in a ſort diuided from the fellowſhip of the Saints. And he was alſo cloathed with mortalitie, and in himſelfe ſtill full of frailtie and infirmitie, and yet hee was aſtoniſhed at the view of ſo great glorie.</p>
            <p>But now is Ieſus in heauen, ſitting at the right hand of God, cloathed with maieſtie and glorie. Now is hee accompanied and attended by armies of Saints and Angells. Now is his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie conſtant, and ſhall neuer more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any eclips. The Saintes that now come vnto him, by putting off their bodies in death, they put off mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, corruption, frailty, and all infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, they are brought by Angells into the ſocietie of Saints and Angells, as
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:25239:28"/>the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes ſpeaketh in the 12. chapter, the 22. verſe: <hi>Ye are come vnto the mounts Sion, and to the Citie of the liuing God, the celeſtiall Ieruſalem, and to the company of innumerable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, and to the congregation of the first borne, which are written in heauen, and to God the Iudge of all, and to the ſpirits of iuſt and perfect men, and to Ieſus to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of the new Teſtament.</hi> And while thus accompanied, they behold the glory of Chriſt, themſelues ſhall bee transformed into glory.</p>
            <p>Our iudgement eſteeming of this happineſſe to be with Chriſt, may be directed and helped ſomething by our wordes in recounting this happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But yet neither can our wordes expreſſe, nor our heart fully conceiue the great happineſſe that the Saints of God finde, when departing from vs, they come vnto the Lord Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Is not the naturall childe glad to be with his father, and doth he not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:25239:29"/>find content? Is not the louing wife ſatisfied to bee in company with her kinde husband, and dooth not that pleaſe her minde? Is not a true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and faithfull friend glad to enioy the companie of a true hearted and faithfull friend, and doe not they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing met, reioyce togither? Euen ſo the Chriſtian ſoule that loueth the Lorde Ieſus, will deſire to bee looſed and to bee with Chriſt, for it knoweth that to be beſt.</p>
            <p>Such to be the deſire of a true holie ſoule, euen by death to come vnto him, rather then by ſtill liuing here, to be kept from him, may appeare by the words of priuate meditation, that <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> vſeth in the firſt chapter of his <hi>Soliloquia,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Cur faciem tuam ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcondis? forte dices non videbit me homo &amp; viuet. Eia Domine, moriar vt te videa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, videam vt hic moriar, nolo viuere, volo mori, diſſolui cupio &amp; eſſe cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſto, mori deſidero vt videa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Christum, viuere renue
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:25239:29"/>vt vivam cum Chriſto. O Domine Ieſu accipe ſpiritum meum, vita mea ſuſcipe animam meam, gaudium meum attrahe cor meum.</hi> That is, why dooſt thou hide thy face? Thou wilt ſay perhaps, no man ſhall ſee me, and liue. Come on then Lord, let mee die, that I may ſee thee: Let mee ſee thee, though I die here. Oh I deſire not to liue, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to die, I long to bee looſed that I may bee with Chriſt: I wiſh to die, that I may ſee Chriſt, I refuſe to liue, that I may liue with Chriſt. O my Lorde Ieſus receiue my ſpirite, O thou my life, receiue my ſoule, O thou my ioy, drawe my heart vnto thee.</p>
            <p>Thoſe which were preſent with this man in the time of his ſickneſſe, and houre of his death, know with what conſtant deſire he waited for and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his diſſolution: therefore deſiring to die, that hee might be with Chriſt: &amp; therfore deſiring to be with Chriſt,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25239:30"/>becauſe he knew it to be beſt of all.</p>
            <p>That the power of faith, and true knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt hadde wrougth in him, that he preferred Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt before al things, before life, riches, friends, &amp; whatſoeuer, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that to bee with Chriſt, was more then all.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God that is wonderfull in thoſe that beleeue. And let vs by ſuch examples bee moued to treaſure vp faith in Chriſt. The Apoſtle ſaith in his Epiſtle to the Philippians, 3. chapter, 17. verſe, <hi>Looke on them which walke ſo, as they haue vs for an example.</hi> The Apoſtle himſelfe was the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. He deſired <hi>to be looſed, that he might be with Christ, which is beſt of all.</hi> This man walked ſo, for hee deſired to bee looſed, that he might be with Chriſt, knowing that to be beſt of all. Let vs looke vpon him, and while wee haue time &amp; helpes, let vs lay hold on faith, that knowing death to bee the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:25239:30"/>of vs vnto Chriſt, and that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of Chriſt to be the higheſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, wee may with quiet and glad mindes, put off our fleſh, when the day of our diſſolution commeth, and may reſt in the Lord, as this our Brother doth.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Laus Deo.</hi> Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
